The next of the normalcytic endemias are those with predominantly intravascular hemolysis,
and the first of them that we want to cover is paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria.
I actually prefer to explain this in my own words, and then I'll walk you through the slides,
so let's just take a blank screen for a second and remind ourselves of a couple points.
First of all, the red blood cells, they live in a very dangerous environment.
They live right next to complement. Their neighbors are deadly.
And so the red blood cell needs to be protected against complement,
and in fact, this doesn't apply to the red blood cell only.
It also applies to the platelets and the white cells as well.
And so the red blood cells, in order to protect themselves against being destroyed by their neighbor, i.e. complement,
they actually have a molecule on their surface, and that molecule on their surface is called DAF, decay accelerating factor.
They also have another molecule on their surface, which is called MERL, membrane inhibitor of reactive lysis.
And so these two molecules, what they do is work complement to get activated.
If complement were to try to come anywhere near the red blood cell, these two molecules would inactivate the complement.
DAF stands for decay accelerating factor, and it accelerates the decay of C3 convertase, for example.
Now, it's important to then note that DAF and MERL are both connected to the red blood cell membrane by an anchoring protein called GPI.
So this is GPI.
And this anchoring protein is essential because it's what allows DAF and MERL to be expressed on the surface of the red blood cell.
In paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria, the problem is the patients get an acquired.
Note that it's an acquired.
It's not inherited.
It occurs later in life.
It's an acquired defect in the myeloid stem cell.
And because there is a defect in the myeloid stem cell, GPI will not be present in all cells derived from the myeloid lineage.
So, for example, the platelets will not have GPI.
The red blood cells will not have GPI.
And the white blood cells, in particular the granulocytes, will not have GPI.
And because there is no GPI, there's going to be no DAF.
And if there is no DAF, and there is no MERL, for example, then the cells will be susceptible to destruction by complement.
And that's the problem in paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria.
And that is that the cells are susceptible to complement destruction.
Now, we're not done there.
We've got to go one more step further and explain the name, paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria.
In order to understand this, you have to go back and remind yourselves from physiology,
when we sleep at night, we actually breathe shallow.
And when our breathing becomes shallow, we retain carbon dioxide.
And when we retain carbon dioxide, that then gives us a respiratory acidosis.
Now, acidosis has the ability to activate complement.
So, at night, we are activating a little bit of complement.
Of course, patients who have normal red blood cells and normal white blood cells and normal platelets
would have no problem with this activation.
They could simply protect themselves against that activation.
However, in patients who have an absent GPI and don't have these protective molecules,
they will be susceptible to complement mediated damage in particular or classically when they're sleeping at night.
And so that's why it's called paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria because on some nights, i.e. paroxysmal,
when the patients are sleeping, they actually get lysis of their red cells and platelets and granulocytes,
but in particular, they're red cells, which then results in the hemoglobinuria.
When they wake up in the morning, they've got very dark urine.
So that's the summary.
Now, let me walk you through what the text says.
Paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria is an acquired defect.
That's important.
In the myeloid stem cell, that's important.
Results in absent GPI.
This then renders the cell susceptible to complement because there is no DAF and there is no MERL present on their cell surface.
In particular, the patients get intravascular hemolysis that occurs at night.
Intravascular because the complement destroys the red blood cell within the blood vessel at night because that's when complement gets activated.
Why does it get activated at night?
Because there's shallow breathing resulting in a respiratory acidosis, which then results in activation of complement.
And, of course, the red blood cells, the granulocytes, and the platelets are all lysed because each of these cells are lacking the GPI linker molecule.
This presents with intravascular hemolysis, so the patients present with hemoglobinemia.
If you were to look in their blood, you would see hemoglobin.
Some of that hemoglobin will leak out into the urine, giving you hemoglobinuria.
And also, some of the hemoglobin in the urine will be taken up by the tubular cells in the kidney.
And as it piles up in the tubular cells of the kidney, it'll pile up as hemocytorin.
Now, eventually, the tubular cells of the kidney will be sloughed off as they turn over, and that'll give us hemocytorinuria.
But that will be seen days after the hemolysis.
So it won't be seen with the acute episode.
But it might be useful if you're suspecting hemolysis and you want to check for it days after the event occurred.
One way by which we can screen for this disease is to introduce sucrose into the patient's serum.
When we introduce sucrose, that activates complement, and that could then destroy the red blood cells in a screening test.
A confirmatory test would be to acidify the serum.
If you acidify the serum, you would activate complement, which would then also confirm the disease.
Nowadays, the more recent test and the test that's more often used in laboratories today is to look for a lack of CD55 on the surface of the red blood cells.
If you have red blood cells and you want to see whether they have CD55, an important thing about CD55 is that it uses GPI as a linker molecule.
So if there is a population of red cells in the patient that lacks CD55, that would be a way by which you could prove that the patient has paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobin area.
And CD55 really is DAF, so that makes sense because DAF was the whole molecule that we started this discussion with.
The main cause of death in patients is thrombosis.
The idea here is that the complement is going to destroy the red cells, the platelets, and the granulocytes.
And so when it destroys the platelets, the fragments of the destroyed platelets can actually go into the circulation,
and that can activate the coagulation cascade, resulting in thrombosis.
And so that's the main cause of death.
And so examiners love to go after it because it really tests you on two principles.
One, you need to remember that the platelets are also lacking GPI.
And two, that's the major cause of death in these patients, thrombosis of hepatic vein or portal vein or cerebral veins, for example.
Complications of the disease include iron deficiency anemia.
Why would they get iron deficiency anemia?
The answer is these patients are losing iron in their urine.
As they're losing hemoglobin, they're actually losing iron.
And so they can develop an iron deficiency anemia.
In addition, 10% of the patients can develop AML.
Now remember that I told you that this disease is a mutation in the myeloid stem cell.
So imagine if there's one mutation in the myeloid stem cell, it's not going to be hard to develop another mutation in that cell,
and eventually that could result in AML.
And 10% of the patients do develop AML, and that is a high-yield association as well.
The second of the predominantly intravascular hemolysis disorders is G6PD deficiency.
G6PD deficiency, again, requires a little bit of biochemistry to understand,
so what I prefer to do is explain it in my own way, and then I'll walk you through the slides.
When you think about G6PD deficiency, what you need to understand is that the red blood cells,
they live in an environment of oxidative stress.
The red blood cells, they live in an environment of oxidative stress.
To protect themselves against that oxidative stress, for example, just by the fact that they carry oxygen,
by the fact that there's going to be inflammation in the body, etc., those are all oxidative stresses.
To protect themselves against oxidative stress, they use a special molecule called glutathione.
So glutathione is very important to protect against oxidative stress.
For example, H2O2, which is one of the major sources of oxidative stress, can be taken by glutathione,
and it can be reduced such that glutathione will reduce it and then become oxidized itself, resulting in GSSG.
Now, when glutathione gets oxidized and takes the hit to protect the cell against H2O2,
that's great because it protects it against an oxidative stress.
However, in order to continue to protect the cell against oxidative stress,
it needs to be reduced back into glutathione.
The molecule that's necessary to do this is NADPH.
And NADPH is produced via G6PD, glucose 6-phosphate dehydrogenase.
So one of the byproducts of glucose 6-phosphate dehydrogenase is NADPH.
No glucose 6-phosphate dehydrogenase, i.e., glucose 6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency, means no NADPH.
No NADPH means no ability to regenerate reduced glutathione.
No ability to regenerate reduced glutathione means that there's going to be increased oxidative damage to the red blood cells.
So that is G6PD deficiency in a nutshell.
Now let's walk through the slides.
So in G6PD deficiency, it's an X-linked recessive disorder with a reduced half-life.
That's important, reduced half-life.
I'll highlight that in a moment.
This renders the cells susceptible to oxidative stress.
Now G6PD has two major variants.
There's an African variant where there's a mildly reduced half-life, and there's a Mediterranean variant where there's a markedly reduced half-life.
The high gene frequency in both of these populations is because it has a protective role against falciparum, malaria.
Let me go back and just remind you that when we talk about the two variants,
the two variants can result in somewhat different clinical severity of disease.
So remember that in the African variant, there is a mildly reduced half-life of G6PD.
So let's just draw a few cells.
Let's pretend this is 30 days old, 60 days old, 90 days old, and 120 days old.
So 30, 60, 90, and 120.
And let's draw this same thing here.
30, 60, 90, and 120.
Now in the mild form, well, why don't we take a step back?
In the normal patient, G6PD's half-life is such that it lasts the entire life of the red blood cell,
so that a normal red blood cell, no matter how old it is, has sufficient G6PD.
In the mildly reduced half-life, the G6PD is not present in cells that are older because, obviously, they've lived longer,
and the half-life of the enzyme was not able to allow the enzyme to be present for a long period of time.
So in a mildly reduced half-life, maybe only the older cells don't have G6PD.
So if there's an oxidative stress, then what will happen is only the cells that are older will be destroyed,
and that's the African variant.
In the Mediterranean variant, where there's a markedly reduced half-life, the G6PD is removed much earlier.
And so, for example, when there's an oxidative stress, all these cells at greater than the age of 30 days, for example, will die.
And that's because there is a markedly reduced half-life of G6PD.
Now, what are the oxidative stresses to be aware of?
Well, the causes of oxidative stress include infections, drugs, and fava beans.
And fava beans are classic, especially in the Mediterranean variant, because they are particularly consumed in the Mediterranean regions.
When the oxidative stress hits the cell, then that causes hemoglobin to precipitate as a Heinz body.
The precipitate of hemoglobin is then removed by the splenic macrophages, resulting in bite cells.
And that then results in intravascular hemolysis.
Now, there may be some extravascular hemolysis, in that the macrophages may sometimes consume the entire cell, rather than just creating a bite.
But the predominant hemolysis is intravascular.
Here's an example of a bite cell.
The splenic macrophage has taken a bite out of this cell.
And the idea here is that if there is a big precipitative hemoglobin, the splenic macrophage will simply remove that.
And when it removes it, it's going to end up removing a big piece of the cell with it.
Now, these patients are then going to get intravascular hemolysis.
This presents with hemoglobinuria.
So they get hemoglobin in the urine because of intravascular hemolysis.
And classically get back pain because the hemoglobin is nephrotoxic.
And so that results in the back pain that's classically seen.
This occurs hours after exposure to an oxidative stress.
If you want to try to see the precipitated hemoglobin, you won't be able to see it in the normal blood smear.
Instead, a special preparation called the Heinz preparation must be made.
And this will be a screen for the disease.
The Heinz preparation will then highlight the precipitated hemoglobin.
And so here's an example of a Heinz prep showing the aggregate of hemoglobin.
Again, important to note that if you want to confirm the disease, you must do enzymatic studies.
But you will not do the enzymatic studies until after the disease has resolved, i.e. after the acute episode.
If you did the enzymatic studies at the time that there was hemolysis, all the cells that are lacking the enzyme will be dead.
And when you test the remaining red cells, those are the ones that actually have the enzyme because they had a half-life sufficient within that red blood cell.
So we don't do the enzyme test until the patient has actually resolved the acute hemolytic episode.
And that's an important take-home point as well.
Another important cause of hemolysis is immune hemolytic anemia.
Now, immune hemolytic anemia is antibody-mediated destruction of the red blood cells.
And it can be due to IgG or IgM.
If it's due to IgG, that's called IgG-mediated disease, and that usually is extravascular hemolysis.
The idea here is that the IgG will bind the red blood cell.
It's also called a warm agglutinin because it binds the red blood cell in the relatively warm temperature of the central body.
When the RBC is coated with the IgG, the membrane and IgG will actually be eaten up by the splenic macrophages,
and that will slowly remove membrane from the cell.
And the slow loss of membrane from the cell will result in spherocytes.
It's very similar to hereditary spherocytosis.
Again, the idea is that if this is the red blood cell, and you slowly pick off a little bit of membrane using an antibody,
then as you take away more and more membrane, you're going to lose excess membrane, and these cells will convert to spherocytes.
So on blood smear, you would see the same thing that you would see in hereditary spherocytosis.
This IgG-mediated disease is associated with lupus.
And remember that in lupus, you can get antibodies against red cells, antibodies against platelets, or antibodies against white cells.
It's also associated with CLL.
In chronic lymphocytic leukemia, one of the complications is that the patients can actually develop an autoimmune hemolytic anemia, usually IgG,
and it's also associated with certain drugs.
Now, when it's associated with drugs, there's a couple ways by which those antibodies can actually cause destruction.
One way is that the drug can actually attach to the red blood cell membrane,
and that occurs, for example, with penicillin, and then the antibody will bind the drug membrane complex,
and that will then allow for removal of pieces of membrane.
Another way is that the drug can actually induce production of autoantibodies itself,
i.e. the drug causes the production of autoantibodies.
An example of that would be methyl dopa,
and those antibodies then bind antigens that are present already on the red blood cell.
So that's a couple mechanisms of how drugs might result in autoimmune hemolytic anemia.
The treatment is going to be to remove the drug, if it's indeed caused by a drug.
Steroids, to slow down the production of the antibody.
I.V.I.G., this is IV immunoglobulin, and the idea here is that if you give IV immunoglobulin,
the splenic macrophages will eat the IV immunoglobulin instead of eating the immunoglobulin attached to the red blood cells.
And so IV.I.G. is like throwing a stick at a dog so that it runs the other way.
You throw a stick at the spleen, so it starts eating the IV.I.G. instead of the red blood cells.
It buys you some time.
And then splenectomy could be performed because there would be two benefits.
Number one, it removes the source of antibody.
And number two, it removes the source of destruction because it's predominantly the spleen that's eating those antibody-bound red blood cells.
And so that's a little bit about treatment.
Of course, splenectomy is the last resort.
I.G.M.-mediated disease usually involves intravascular hemolysis,
and the idea here is that I.G.M. binds RBCs, usually in the colder temperature of the extremities,
for example, the fingers and the toes.
It then fixes complement, and when it fixes complement, that results in formation of a membrane attack complex,
which then results in an intravascular hemolysis.
Now, this is associated with two very high-yield concepts.
Number one, mycoplasma pneumoniae.
Patients with mycoplasma pneumoniae can subsequently develop an I.G.M.-mediated intravascular hemolysis,
which would be autoimmune, and also it can be seen with infectious mononucleosis.
So those are a couple of high-yield associations for I.G.M.-mediated autoimmune destruction of red blood cells.
The Coombs test is what is used to diagnose immune hemolytic anemia.
There are two types of Coombs test.
There's a direct and an indirect.
The idea in the direct Coombs test is that you're asking the question.
Remember, whenever you do a test, you're asking a question.
And so what's the question in this test?
The question is, do I have red blood cells that are already bound by I.G.G.?
So you've got these red blood cells, and they're already bound by I.G.G.,
and you're asking the question, are these present?
So what you do is you introduce another antibody against I.G.G.,
and if this exists, then that will cause agglutination.
It will cause the red cells to pile up and precipitate out.
So that's the direct Coombs test.
You take anti-I.G.G., you add it to the patient's R.B.C.s.
You assume, or you're asking the question, are the R.B.C.s already coded with I.G.G.?
And if they are, agglutination will occur.
This is the most important test for immune hemolytic anemia.
The indirect Coombs test asks a different question.
It asks the question, does the patient have antibodies in their serum?
So now what you're doing is you're taking R.B.C.s from, you know, these are test R.B.C.s,
and you're putting in the patient's serum and asking the question,
are there these antibodies in the serum?
If they are, they'll bind the R.B.C.s,
and you're going to add an anti-I.G.G. antibody,
which will then result in agglutination.
So the direct test asks the question,
do I have red blood cells that are already coded with antibody?
And the indirect test asks the question,
does the patient's serum have the antibody?
So that's important to understand that distinction.
Another way by which we can get intravascular hemolysis
is called microangiopathic hemolytic anemia.
Microangio, small blood vessel, pathic pathology.
So there is a pathology in the small blood vessel
that results in a hemolytic anemia.
Now the idea here is that you've got a small blood vessel,
and of course this blood vessel is lined by endothelial cells.
And what happens in this case
is that you get some sort of thrombus.
It could be a platelet thrombus.
It could be a platelet plus fibrin thrombus,
which blocks the blood vessel partially
so that when the red blood cells go across this blood vessel,
they get sheared,
and they develop into cells that look like this,
which are called schistocytes.
And schistocytes are the hallmark
of microangiopathic hemolytic anemia.
Now microangiopathic hemolytic anemia
can be seen in a few circumstances.
The first would be TTP,
thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura.
And in this particular case,
you get platelet thrombi,
platelet thrombi,
and it's due to the fact
that the patient lacks an enzyme called ADAMS-TS13.
We've discussed this in detail
in our coagulation lecture,
so I won't repeat it here,
but you can refer back there if you need to.
In HUS, which is sort of the sister disease,
you also have platelet microthrombi,
but in hemolytic uremic syndrome, i.e. HUS,
it is due to a toxin produced by E. coli 015787.
Again, we've also covered this in our previous discussions.
In DIC, you get platelet plus fibrin thrombi,
and the platelet fibrin thrombi
would then again result in schistocytes.
We've covered that previously.
And in a fourth scenario called HELP,
hemolysis elevated liver enzymes and low platelets.
A pregnant woman can develop
the microangiopathic hemolytic anemia
within the liver
due to the production of these thrombi as well.
And we'll discuss that in more detail
when we do the gynecologic lectures.
But the idea here is that
you've got a small vessel pathology
that results in production of schistocytes
and a hemolytic anemia.
We can also get loss of red blood cell
within the vasculature with prostatic heart valves,
and that's because the valves crush the red blood cells,
destroying them,
and with aortic stenosis.
The calcified degenerative valve
will also again crush the red blood cells
and destroy them.
So these are some circumstances
in which patients might get
a hemolytic anemia inside the blood vessel.
Again, I've already told you
that microthrombi produce schistocytes on blood smears.
So whenever you have a microangiopathic hemolytic anemia,
you think about schistocytes.
And this is the classic image of schistocytes
that I've already presented in a prior lecture.
Notice that it looks like a helmet,
and that's the classic finding
is that you have points at either end of the cell
with a shearing of the cell across the cytoplasm.
Another way by which red blood cells can be destroyed
is malaria.
Malaria results in infection of the red blood cells
and the liver with plasmodium,
and it's transmitted by the anophilus mosquito,
and that's important to know as well.
This is the classic finding.
We will see little fragments of,
or little organisms,
malarial organisms present within the red blood cells.
It's important to note
that what causes the hemolysis
is that the RBCs rupture as part of the plasmodium life cycle,
so that each time the plasmodium undergoes its life cycle
and begins to reproduce,
eventually it'll cause rupture of the cell.
What's interesting is that the rupture of the cell
will result in fever,
so that, for example,
with plasmodium falciparum,
the patients get daily fever,
whereas with vivax and ovale,
they get fever every other day.
So, again, just highlighting,
just allowing you to remember that in malaria,
patients would also get
a predominantly intravascular hemolysis.
However, the spleen will also consume
some of the infected red blood cells,
and so there will be some extravascular hemolysis
with splenomegaly.
The final discussion that we want to have
is anemias due to underproduction,
and the idea here, again,
is that you get decreased production
of the red blood cells by the bone marrow,
and it's characterized
by a low corrected reticulocyte count.
The etiologies of underproduction bone marrow include
anything that causes a microcytic anemia
or a macrocytic anemia
will usually have a low reticulocyte count,
so, for example,
an iron deficiency anemia,
the reticulocyte count tends to be low,
in vitamin B12 and folate deficiency anemia,
the reticulocyte count tends to be low.
Renal failure will also result
in low production by the bone marrow
because there will be less erythropoietin produced,
reticulocyte count will be low,
and if there's damage
to the bone marrow precursor cells,
that would also result
in a low reticulocyte count
because the progenitor cells
are not functioning properly.
One classic example would be parvovirus B19.
We've talked about it several times already,
this infects the progenitor red cells
and then stops erythropoiesis,
which then results in anemia,
predominantly when there's pre-existing marrow stress.
So you and I,
if we got a parvovirus B19 infection,
would probably be relatively asymptomatic,
but a patient who's highly dependent
on their reserve of bone marrow
would show signs,
even with a minimal knockdown
of their erythropoiesis,
or in particular,
their production of red blood cells.
The treatment's supportive
because parvovirus B19 is self-limited.
Usually within a week to 10 days,
the infection begins to resolve.
Aplastic anemia is when you have damage
to the hematopoietic stem cell.
This results in a pancytopenia,
i.e. low white count,
low red blood cells,
and low platelets,
with a low reticulocyte count
because you're not making red blood cells.
Etiologies include drugs and chemicals.
There are some drugs and chemicals
that can classically result in aplastic anemia.
Viral infections can also do it.
And last cause would be autoimmune damage.
When a biopsy is performed
in this particular case,
the classic finding
is that there is an empty marrow.
This is the bone marrow.
Here's the spicule of bone.
And all we see here is fat.
Each of these circles
represents adipose tissue or fat.
And notice that there are basically
no hematopoietic elements
in this marrow space.
So that's aplastic anemia.
The treatment involves cessation
of any drug that might be causing it,
transfusions to support the patient,
and marrow stimulating factors
can be given in order to try
to induce production of cells
from whatever stem cells are present.
So erythropoietin to drive
the erythroid precursors
to produce red cells.
GMCSF and GCSF
to drive the granulocytic precursors
to produce granulocytes.
Another possible treatment
is immunosuppression.
Recall that one of the etiologies
of aplastic anemia is autoimmune.
And so immunosuppression
can potentially knock down
that autoimmunity,
allowing for the bone marrow to come back.
And the final last resort
would be to give
a bone marrow transplant.
The very last topic
that I want to touch on
is a myelophysic process.
This is a pathologic process
that replaces the bone marrow.
So if there's some pathologic process
that takes over the bone marrow,
that would impair hematopoiesis
because that's obviously
where the cells are generated.
For example,
if the patient had metastatic cancer
that diffusely replaces
the bone marrow,
that would impair hematopoiesis
resulting in pancytopenia.
And that is called
a myelophysic process.
And so with that,
we conclude our chapter
on red blood cell disorders.